Earl Browder Papers
Earl Browder Papers
- Writings
  - Speeches
    - 1944 Sep-Dec (Box 66)
      FDR's recent appointments to Department of State, 12/27/1944, Queens County, Daily Worker Campaign Dinner
    - 1945 Jan-May (Box 66)
      "Everything For Victory", 1/15/1945, Lenin Memorial Meeting, Madison Square Garden
      Progressive unity, 1/26/1945, Peter Cacchione Campaign dinner, Brooklyn, NY
      Interview, 3/12/1945, unknown
      Tribute to William Z. Foster, 3/23/1945, Testimonial dinner for William Z. Foster
      "Toward the Organization of World Peace", 4/6/1945, Cleveland, Ohio
      Luncheon remarks, 4/6/1945, Carter Hotel, Cleveland, Ohio
      "Toward the Organization of World Peace", 4/7/1945, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania
      "Roosevelt Continues to Lead America", 4/14/1945, Carnegie Hall, New York
      "Is the American Press doing Its Job?", 5/15/1945, Radio discussion
      Statement on V-E Day, 5/7/1945
      US Communists' role in Post War world, 5/21/1945, Communist Political Association meeting
      First speech on the Duclos article, 5/22/1945, National Board CPA
      Discussion of marxism and politics, 5/23/1945, unknown (CPA meeting?)
      Tribute to Jacques Roumain, 5/24/1945, Times Hall, New York
      "The San Francisco Conference", 5/25/1945, Town Hall Forum
    - 1945 Jun (Box 66)
      "Soviet-American Relations -- Is It War or Peace?", 6/2/1945, CPUSA National Board meeting
      San Francisco Conference (United Nations), 6/4/1945, Manhattan Center [CPA?]
      "Tasks of the American Working Class After V-E Day", 6/18/1945, National Committee (CPA)
      Working Class and War (and Russian translation), 6/18/1945, National Committee (CPA)
      Statement, 6/20/1945, National Committee (CPA)
    - 1945 Jul (Box 66)
      War in the Pacific, 7/26/1945, National Convention CPA
      Foster and Duclos, 7/26/1945, National Convention CPA
    - 1946 (Box 66)
      CP expulsion of Browder, 1/31/1946, Yonkers Club
      CP expulsion of Browder, 2/1/1946, Yonkers Club
      "Russia and America: How Can we Build a Lasting Peace?", 11/6/1946, Norwalk Town Hall Association debate with Clare Booth Luce
      1946 elections, 11/?/1946, unknown
    - 1947 (Box 66)
      One hundredth anniversary of Marx's "Communist Manifesto", 1/19/1947, CBS Radio broadcast on "Invitation to Learning" program
    - 1949 (Box 67)
      "Chinese Lessons for American Marxists", 1/17/1949, Discussion Circle, Woodstock Hotel, New York
      "The Coming Economic Crisis in America", 2/14/1949, Discussion Circle, Woodstock Hotel, New York
      "War, Peace and Socialism", 4/11/1949, Forum Group, Caravan Hall, New York
      "A Market Program for American Progressives", 5/2/1949, Forum Group, Pythian Temple, New York
      "How to Halt Crisis and War", 5/2/1949, Forum Group, Pythian Temple, New York
      "The USA and the USSR: Their Relative Strength" (and Russian translation), 6/6/1949, Forum Group, Pythian Temple, New York
      "Toward and American Peace Policy", ?/?/1949, unknown
    - 1950-1956 (Box 67)
      "Is Russia A Socialist Community?", 3/30/1950, Debate, Eugene V. Debs Society of Brooklyn College, New York
      Protest against arrest of Communists, 6/20/1951, Statement given to NBC
      "Should Soviet China Be Admitted to the United Nations?", 11/7/1951, Parkway Community Council, Brooklyn, NY
      "Crisis of American Progressivism", 6/3/1952, unknown
      Statement to the Court re:Mrs. Browder's passport case, ?/?/1952
      Interview about Prague Trials, 1/30/1953, unknown
      Inteview about Soviet purges, 2/10/1953, Telepress Daily TV News Reel
      History of Communism Interview 1, 5/19/1953, unknown
      History of Communism Interview 2, 6/2/1953, unknown
      History of Communism Interview 3, 6/16/1953, unknown
      History of Communism Interview 4, 9/29/1953, unknown
      History of Communism Interview 5, 5/4/1954, unknown
      Interview, 7/6/1955, W. Goldsmith
      Interview, 10/26/1955, Sarah Lawrence College
      Civil rights, 9/15/1956, Nassau-Suffolk Socialist Party
    - 1957 Nov, 1 folder of 5 (Box 67)
      "Marxism and America" also called "Karl Marx and America," multiple copies, multiple versions, 11/?/1957, Series of lectures first given at Rutgers University, New Brunswick, New Jersey
      ,
    - 1957 Nov, 4 folders of 5 (Box 68)
    - 1958-1962 (Box 69)
      "Socialism in America", 12/4/1958, St. Anthony's College, Oxford, England
      "Socialism in the Sixties", 8/18/1961, Lecture at Socialist Party Forum, Channing Hall, Los Angeles, California
      "International Relations -- Whither?", 1/9/1962, Economics Club discussion
      "What Has Happened to Socialism?", 3/16/1962, Lecture, Toronto, ON
    - 1963-1967 (Box 69)
      "On the Sino-Soviet Conflict", 3/21/1963, Lecture, Students' Council, Hofstra University, Hempstead, NY
      "The American Communist Party in the 1930's", 3/9/1966, Lecture, University of Illinois, Urbana, Illinois
      "Where Marx Went Wrong", 5/16/1967, Lecture, State College of Iowa, Cedar Falls, IA
    - Date unknown (Box 69)
      American youth movement, unknown
      Comments on Norman Levinson's criticism
      Debate rebuttal
      "Farmer-Labor Party Perspective"
      Filing of objections against the CP State ticket in New York, press statement
      Gretings to Brazilian CP and Luis Carlos Prestes
      Lecture on history of Communism
      Party Building, CP Party Building Conference
      Peter Caccione campaign (incomplete)
      2 page fragment
      10 page fragment
- Memorabilia
  - Address books, address lists
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 70)
  - Artwork
    - Bohnen, Carl, photograph of pencil portrait of Harold Stassen (Oversize 3)
    - Oak, Liston M., woodcut portraits of Stalin and Lenin (Oversize 3)
    - Rico, Dan, woodcut portrait of earl Browder (Oversize 3)
    - Jordan, Theodore Jr., pencil portrait of Tom Mooney (Oversize 3)
    - Gropper, William, pen and ink drawing of woman at sewing machine (Oversize 3)
    - Gibson, Lydia, photograph of oil painting "The Delegates" (Oversize 3)
    - Jacobi, Lotte, pencil portrait and etching (Oversize 3)
  - Clippings
    - About Browder, 1919-1965; 25 folders (Box 71)
    - General, 1929-1972; undated; 4 folders (Box 72)
    - Amerasia, 1947 (Box 72)
    - America, 1940 (Box 72)
    - Chicago Herald American, 1943 (Box 72)
    - China Weekly Review, 1947 (Box 72)
    - Commentary, 1965 (Box 72)
    - Conference Record: Proceedings of the American Jewish Conference, 1943 (Box 72)
    - The Daily Compass, 1951 (Box 72)
    - The Daily News (New York), 1946 (Box 72)
    - Daily Worker, assorted issues (Oversize 1)
    - For A Lasting Peace, For A People's Democracy, 1951 (Box 73)
    - Foreign Affairs, 1969 (Box 73)
    - Foreign Policy Bulletin, 1943 (Box 73)
    - International Judicial Association Monthly Bulletin, 1942 (Box 73)
    - Journal of Historical Studies, 1969 (Box 73)
    - Krokodil (КРОКОДИЛ), 1946 (Box 73)
    - Lawyers Guild Review, 1943 (Box 73)
    - Moscow News, 1987 (Box 73)
    - National Legionnaire, 1936 (Box 73)
    - National Legionnaire. assorted issues (Oversize 1)
    - Neues Leben, 1987 (Box 73)
    - New Republic "Voter's Handbook", 1936 (Box 73)
    - The Norwalk Hour, Norwalk, Connecticut, 1946 (Box 73)
    - The Outlook, 1916 (Box 73)
    - Party Organizer, 1943 (Box 73)
    - Political Affairs, 1945 (Box 73)
    - Political cartoons, 1944-1945 (Box 73)
    - Scope, 1965 (Box 73)
    - Soviet Life, 1987 (Box 73)
    - Spanish Information Service texts and documents, 1938 (Box 73)
    - Vneshniaia Torgovlia (ВНЕШНЯЯ ТОРГОВЛЯ) (tr. Foreign Trade), 1945 (Box 73)
    - The Worker, assorted issues (Oversize 1)
    - Worker's World (Kansas City), 1919 (Oversize 1)
    - Yale News, 1943 (Box 73)
    - Scrapbooks, 1940-1950 (Box 74)
  - Family
    - Browder, Andrew, 1942-1963 (Box 75)
    - Browder, Felix, 1927-1975; 4 folders (Box 75)
    - Browder, Irene, undated; notes for autobiography (Box 75)
    - Browder, William, 1944-1953; 2 folders of 5 (Box 75)
    - Browder, William, 1962-1986; undated; 3 folders of 5 (Box 76)
  - Financial
    - Browder, Earl
      - General, 1944-1965 (Box 77)
      - Income tax returns, 1938-1962 (Box 77)
      - Social Security, 1947-1959 (Box 77)
    - Browder, Felix, 1947-1958 (Box 77)
    - Browder, Ralph Waldo, 1934-1965 (Box 77)
    - [Earl] Browder, Inc.
      - Bills, 1946-1951 (Box 78)
      - Certificate of Dissolution, 1945 (Box 78)
      - Checkbook, 1945 (Box 78)
      - Taxes, 1946-1951 (Box 78)
      - Corporate seal embossing tool, undated (Box 78)
    - Distributors Guide, Inc.
      - Bills and expenses, 1946 (Box 79)
      - Checkbook, 1944-1945 (Box 79)
      - Minutes and by-laws (Box 79)
      - Stock and transfer ledger (Box 79)
      - Stock certificates (Box 79)
  - Photographs
    - Abraham Lincoln Brigade, 1937; undated (Box 80)
    - Averbuck, Nathan Earl, 1939 (Box 80)
    - Billings, Warren, undated (Box 80)
    - Bloor, Ella Reeve, undated (Box 80)
    - Bloor, Ella Reeve, photo of portrait sculpture by A. Cortas, undated (Box 80)
    - Browder family portraits by Lotte Jacobi (Oversize 2)
    - Browder family snapshots, 1930-1960 (Box 80)
    - Browder, Andrew, 1940-1960 (Box 80)
    - Browder, Earl
      - [General], 1901-1927; 1935-1937; 2 folders (Box 80)
      - Autographed, 1935-1960; undated (Box 80)
      - 1936 campaign (Oversize 2)
      - and family, NY World's Fair, 1939 (Box 80)
      - and Raisa, 1935; 1952,; undated (Box 80)
      - in China, 1927 (Box 80)
      - in Terre Haute, IN, 1936 (Box 80)
      - Leaving for Atlanta (prison), 1941 (Box 80)
      - with James Ford, 1936 (Box 80)
      - with James Ford and William Foster, 1936 (Box 80)
      - with Tom Mann, 1927 (Box 80)
      - with Robert Minor, undated (Box 80)
      - with Tom Mooney, Warren Billings and Seymour Waldman, 1939 (Box 80)
      - with "Scottsboro Boys", 1937 (Box 80)
    - Browder, Felix, 1929-1961 (Box 80)
    - Browder, Felix, Andrew and William, 1935-1950 (Box 81)
    - Browder, Gladys Groves, undated (Box 81)
    - Browder, Raissa, undated (Box 81)
    - Browder, William and Martha Jane (neé Hankins), historic family photographs, 1870-1940 (Box 81)
    - Browder, William (brother of EB), 1920-1960 (Box 81)
    - Browder, William (son of E.B.), 1950-1960 (Box 81)
    - Communist International 7th World Congress (see also: ovesize Box 2), 1935 (Box 81)
    - Communist Party meetings, 1937; undated (Oversize 2)
    - Communist Party Canada
      - Memorial to Mackenzie Papineau Battalion, 1938 (Box 81)
      - National Convention delegates, 1938 (Box 81)
    - Communist Party, Mexico panorama, 1939; 1964 (Oversize 2)
    - Communist Party USA
      - May Day Parade, Chicago, 1938 (Box 81)
      - National Nominating Convention, 1936 (Box 81)
      - Rally in Chicago, 1937 (Box 81)
    - Corretjer, Juan Antonio, 1943 (Box 81)
    - Cush, Emmet "Pat", undated (Box 81)
    - Delegates to the Twentieth Anniversary of the October Revolution, Moscow, 1937 (Box 81)
    - Edward, Prince of Wales, 1934 (Box 81)
    - Einstein, Albert, undated (Box 81)
    - Foster, William Zebulon, undated (Box 81)
    - Flynn, Elizabeth Gurley, undated (Box 81)
    - Ford, James W., undated (Box 81)
    - Gren, Gil, undated (Box 81)
    - Heller, Abraham A., undated (Oversize 2)
    - Herndon, Angelo, undated (Box 81)
    - Hoffa, James Riddle, undated (Box 81)
    - Jacobi, Lotte, photographs by, See also Oversize Box 2: Browder family portraits (Box 81)
    - Kalinin, Mikhail Ivanovich, 1934 (Box 81)
    - Lewis, John Llewellyn, undated (Oversize 2)
    - Li Li-San, undated (Box 81)
    - Lindbergh, Charles, undated (Box 81)
    - Lunacharsky, Anatoly, 1930 (Box 81)
    - Mann, Tom, 1933 (Box 81)
    - Minor, Robert, undated (Box 81)
    - "Meet the Press", 1950 (Box 81)
    - Mooney, Tom, undated (Box 82)
    - Mural, "Communism is 20th Century Americanism", undated (Box 82)
    - National Council of Soviet-American Friendship dinner, 1942 (Oversize 2)
    - Nikolauk, Domenica "Nanya", undated (Box 82)
    - Nobile, Umberto, undated (Box 82)
    - Saltonstall, Leverett A., undated (Box 82)
    - Silver Ponds Children's Home, Stalingrad, undated (Box 82)
    - Son Chen Ging, 1927 (Box 82)
    - Soong Ching Ling, undated (Box 82)
    - Soviet Union
      - American students, 1934 (Box 82)
      - Anniversary, 15th, 1932 (Box 82)
      - Anniversary, 16th, 1933 (Box 82)
      - Anniversary, 17th, 1934 (Box 82)
      - Bakhchikarsky, undated (Box 82)
      - Baku, undated (Box 82)
      - Batumi, undated (Box 82)
      - Essentuki, undated (Box 82)
      - Karakol, undated (Box 82)
      - Kiev, undated (Box 82)
      - Kislovodsk, undated (Box 82)
      - Kuzbass, undated (Box 82)
      - Leningrad, undated (Box 82)
      - May Day Parade, Leningrad, undated (Box 82)
      - May Day Parades, Moscow, 1931-1936; undated (Box 82)
      - Moscow, undated (Box 82)
      - Odessa, undated (Box 82)
      - people, undated (Box 82)
      - Rostov-on-Don, undated (Box 82)
      - Sevastopol, undated (Box 82)
      - Sochi, undated (Box 82)
      - Stalingrad, undated (Box 82)
      - Tiflis, undated (Box 82)
      - Tver, undated (Box 82)
      - Uzbekistan, undated (Box 82)
      - Yalta, undated (Box 82)
      - Unidentified places, undated (Box 82)
    - Spanish Civil War, "Training Camp #5", undated (Box 82)
    - Thye, Edward John, undated (Box 82)
    - Trans-Polar Aviators, 1937 (Box 82)
    - de Visser, Louis, undated (Box 82)
    - Wan Min, undated (Box 82)
    - Yarborough, Ralph Webster, undated (Box 82)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 82)
  - Postcards
    - American Airlines, undated (Box 83)
    - Arles, France, undated (Box 83)
    - Atlanta, Georgia, undated (Box 83)
    - Belgium, 1930 (Box 83)
    - Bismark, North Dakota, undated (Box 83)
    - Butte, Montana, undated (Box 83)
    - Chicago, Illinois, undated (Box 83)
    - Cleveland, Ohio, undated (Box 83)
    - Colorado, undated (Box 83)
    - Cunard White Star Lines, undated (Box 83)
    - Florida, 1938; undated (Box 83)
    - France, Pyrénées Orientales, undated (Box 83)
    - Germany, undated (Box 83)
    - Glendale, California, undated (Box 83)
    - Golden Gate International Exposition, 1939 (Box 83)
    - Louvre Museum, undated (Box 83)
    - Massachusetts, 1937; 1941 (Box 83)
    - Mexico, undated (Box 83)
    - New Hampshire, 1940 (Box 83)
    - New Jersey, 1936 (Box 83)
    - New York City, undated (Box 83)
    - New York State, 1937,1938; undated (Box 83)
    - New York World's Fair, 1939 (Box 83)
    - North Carolina, undated (Box 83)
    - Novelty, undated (Box 83)
    - Oregon, undated (Box 83)
    - Paris, 1937; undated (Box 83)
    - Pennsylvania, undated (Box 83)
    - St. Louis, Missouri, undated (Box 84)
    - Salt Lake City, Utah, undated (Box 84)
    - Soviet Union
      - Baku, 1927 (Box 84)
      - Breastfeeding campaign, undated (Box 84)
      - Crimea, 1925 - 1929 (Box 84)
      - Gagri, 1927 (Box 84)
      - Kislovodsk, undated (Box 84)
      - Moscow, undated (Box 84)
      - Nizhny Novgorod, undated (Box 84)
      - Novorossiysk, 1927 (Box 84)
      - Sochi, 1928 (Box 84)
      - Ural Mountains, 1928 (Box 84)
    - Spanish Civil War, undated (Box 84)
    - Tennessee, undated (Box 84)
    - United Airlines, undated (Box 84)
    - Union Pacific Railroad Pictorial Series, undated (Box 84)
    - Vienna, 1948 (Box 84)
    - Virginia, undated (Box 84)
    - Warsaw, Poland, undated (Box 84)
    - Washington, DC
      - Aerial views, undated (Box 84)
      - Buildings, undated (Box 84)
      - Cherry blossoms, undated (Box 84)
    - Yugoslavia, undated (Box 84)
  - Printed material
    - Manet Peintures Les Éditions du Chêne, 1949 (Oversize 3)
    - Song sheets (Box 85)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 85)
  - Sound recordings
    All recordings have been digitized.
    - America and the Soviet-German Pact, undated; browder_e_17
    - Brooklyn Speech, Copy 3, Sides 1 and 3, undated; browder_e_18
    - Brooklyn Speech, Copy 4, Sides 2 and 4, undated; browder_e_19
    - Browder Acceptance Speech, 6/2/1940; browder_e_03, browder_e_04; 2 discs / 4 sides
    - Earl Browder, 9/25/1940; browder_e_05, browder_e_06; 2 discs / 4 sides
    - Earl Browder, 10/13/40; browder_e_21, browder_e_21; 2 discs / 4 sides
    - Earl Browder Foreign Policy, 10/6/[40?]; browder_e_10, browder_e_11, browder_e_12; 3 discs / 6 sides
    - Earl Browder Foreign Policy WABC, 10/10/40; browder_e_08, browder_e_09; 2 discs / 4 sides
    - Earl Browder Says: Excerpts from Speech of Feb. 24, 1941, browder_e_07
    - James Ford Acceptance Speech, 6/2/1940; browder_e_13
    - Mike Wallace interview, 20 Jun 1957; browder_e_23, browder_e_24; Earl Browder on the Mike Wallace Show
    - Mike Wallace interview, 26 Feb 1957; browder_e_25, browder_e_26; Earl Browder segment on Mike Wallace's Night Beat
    - The Most Peculiar Election Campaign, 8 Sep 1940; browder_e_14, browder_e_15, browder_e_16; 3 discs / 6 sides
    - The Quiet Man from Kansas, undated; browder_e_34
      Lyrics by Mark Hess, original music by Frank Pearson, soloist Arthur Atkins with the American People's Chorus; distributed by Workers' Book Shop in New York City
    - To Youth, 10/4/1940; browder_e_01, browder_e_02; 2 discs / 4 sides
    - Soundscriber discs, undated; includes Browder, Luce, rebuttals,; browder_e_29, browder_e_30, browder_e_31, browder_e_32, browder_e_33; 5 discs, 10 sides
    - [Unlabeled], browder_e_27, browder_e_28; cardboard with nitrocellulose lacquer; 2 discs
    - [Unlabeled - W I and W II], browder_e_20; W 1 - initial call and W 2 - follow up; "Phone taps" of calls.
  - Travel souvenirs
    - "Asian Administrative-Political Districts of the Soviet Union", 1929 (Box 85)
    - French Line Ile-de-France baggage sticker, undated (Box 85)
    - Hong Kong Labor Committee delegate medallions, 1927 (Box 85)
    - Leningrad tour book, 1987 (Box 85)
    - "Liste des Passagers" Ile-de-France, 1935 (Box 85)
    - Map of China (in Russian), 1933 (Box 85)
    - Map of the Moscow Metro, undated (Box 85)
    - "Pictorial Street Map of Moscow" (Intourist), undated (Box 85)
    - Memorabilia, Andrew Browder (Oversize 1)
    - Memorabilia, William Browder (Oversize 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 85)
    - Miscellaneous empty portfolios (Box 86)
    - Necktie, black (Box 86)